this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software digital ocean is the easiest
cloud platform to deploy manage and
scale applications of any size we're
moving infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software that
customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials in an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
100 dollar infrastructure credit at doco
/ SC radio welcome everyone to the
software engineering radio show today
my name is Kim Carter I'll be your host
for the day and we've got Michael Rosen
bless is gifts today Michael works read
hit in the openshift team he's a gopher
that's a goal in programmer a cloud
native ambassador and Michael tries to
help folks to be successful with
container technologies including docker
CRI - Oh kubernetes and openshift
michael has written books on container
networking kubernetes and service ops
welcome to the show Michael thanks a lot
for having me Kim we have hid shows on
docker with James Turnbull that was show
number 217 and have hid docker security
with Diego moniker that was show number
290 and another show of head it was
related as network security with her own
Mia that was show number 302 there's a
relevant article from the I Triple E
Computer Society on today's topic its
docker in another one a network quality
of service and docker containers today
we're going to be discussing a container
networking so I'm just starting off with
the container networking stack what is
container networking and why do we need
Shaniqua containers right let's step
back so like what are containers like
essentially a way to handle application
level dependency management so you know
if you're for example no Python and you
know you have virtual ends there where
where you can create virtual
environments for for Python rather than
polluting the global space that's the
same thing with containers just for any
kind of language and binaries and so on
so containers package your application
level dependencies nicely can ship them
you know works the same on your laptop
and production everywhere and at the end
of the day you know you can run a
container on your laptop and you know
you can run a bunch of them where you
can run many of them and then you need
container orchestration you know the
things like who it is that actually
manage these containers for you at scale
and one of the big challenges there is
actually how these applications in the
containers communicate with each other
and for that we need container
networking sure so let's talk a little
bit about the networking stick and what
it's comprised of when it comes to
containers can you explain briefly the
three layers so it's a a low level
networking containing it working in
container orchestration right so in
other said this is not like you know
what seems like yours I stack or TCP
stacks I'm something official it's just
something I came up with to easier
explain stuff and make it easier for
people to understand what is going on
there so the way I approach it is to
look at lower or low level stuff and it
includes everything right do you have
the the networking gear the actual
hardware you might have
Burton machine virtualized stuff in
there you know you have IP Te'o
loose-leaf Linux kernel features in
there if routing you have Linux
namespaces cgroups and so on so
everything all these bits and pieces
that usually from a developer
perspective you don't really care about
you don't actually see them touch them
usually but they exist and do you you
know you should be aware there is the
container layer that is mainly around
the extra container runtime so the thing
that essentially made docker
you know
popular and baked nowadays we have OCI
the the open container initiative and
with Rockhead we have a couple of specs
there and if we get to that back later
on the CNI and CNM yeah so this is
everything around the the container
runtime really on that layer and on top
of that as I mentioned really early on
if you you know manually launch your
container here they are but you're kind
of like on an industrial scale launching
and killing off containers then you have
a container orchestration system like
when it is in place and there you have
the actual container orchestration layer
so everything around you know service
discovery ingress egress how you compose
things there it might go so far that you
have you know service measures there
that's even sit on top of this container
orchestration there or some people
consider them part of it but it helps to
think along these three layers because
they typically are owned by different
interesting holders or or different
people focus on them we talked about a
bit here on most networks today are
becoming other responsibilities of
software engineers there was an show 302
a network security with her in Mir I
also cover this in my book on cloud
security
can you explain what Software Defined
done it working is and why software
engineers need to understand about it
I'm not sure if many people will be
super happy with with my definition of
it but at least that's how I see it to
me it's really marketing term to be
honest it's a useful term but it's
almost like like you know the term
overlay network it's pretty broad and
depending on who you talk to which when
they're you're talking to and so on you
will hear different things you know
different people if you ask some
Fransisco and whatnot
you will hear different things what I
will say is the most important
characteristic and then that's what we
are leveraging in the container world is
that rather than being confined by by
the the physical things that are in
there like a physical nake and and you
know actual cables and so on and so
forth you are on a virtual level right
you are essentially you can via software
define pretty much everything you can
say hey I want to have three three NIC
here you define endpoints you define you
can give a piece to containers and so on
so forth so routing tables everything
everything is on the software level
everything is super flexible there and
that allows and in the container world
with with you know a container
Orchestrator with many many containers
that come and go this is really the only
way to go about you cannot manually keep
up with with the pace that is going on
there and so in the sense as I said it's
s has many other things like like overly
networking it's a bit of a marketing
term but the main thing really is you're
much more flexible and can automate the
heck out of it so you'd use tools like T
reform and that sort of thing to build
up you network software right so that
you can basically rip I repeatedly
create them is it pretty much what some
of that yeah yeah yeah because if you
think about you know like five or ten
years ago maybe 15 years ago we might
have had like a handful of virtual
machines that we would manage that would
stay around for a month or years and now
with containers we have hundreds of
containers if not thousands of
containers that you know might only
stick around for a few minutes right so
you do need this flexibility you do need
this velocity there so we're just gonna
move into a section on single host
containing it with so there's four
single host networking modes based on
the for Linux kernel network namespace
drivers the bridge host which is faster
but less secure container and none can
you give us a description of these modes
and what they give us here they work in
and where we would use each one the
background here really is that these
four modes that you mentioned are
essentially have been popularized so has
been established by by docker what a
docker shipped with with its runtime so
bridge which is still the default I said
she sets up via a pair in the the
container which is essentially a network
namespace and the host so you have that
hair there
visibly the obvious advantage that
you're pretty pretty flexible in terms
of ports so you don't need to you can
have for example two containers that
both are surf in Port 80 right that's
something that you usually cannot have
that's the fact that you will usually
cannot bind people o unless you have
privileges below port 1024 a host
networking if you know you essentially
say you know it's it's fine you know
share the network with with the host you
don't really care too much there it's
definitely faster than bridge but you
don't care too much there in terms of
security because it you essentially
effectively removing the isolation their
container that mode is essentially
reusing an existing networks you cannot
like you know in the dock a file
whatever you cannot create that only at
runtime you can say you know here I have
another container already running
please join this this other network here
and we're using that in communities very
heavily so there is actually a component
in every part there that spends up this
this namespace and every every other
container in that pot joins that one and
nonessential means disable it's still
there the networks tag is still there so
you do have loopback interface if you do
you know if config whatever IP come on
but that that's all you cannot you know
use any network you don't have any
external communication there so that all
of them are really useful one way or the
other if you you know let's let's put it
in a very simple terms if you're doing
stuff on your laptop right then then
you're fine right in any kind of
clustered setup if you have a bunch of
machines somewhere even if it's just a
three node cluster none of them right is
really really useful right you would use
other is there a couple of them in dark
hair like overlay and make villain IP
VLAN and there are third-party plugins
possible a couple of them there but
essentially for this use case of running
a handful of containers on a single node
or on your laptop one of those four
might be might be useful so the
container networking mode especially
means every container
is the same network stick right so they
all have the same ip address so how do
you actually differentiate the
containers like how do you actually
contact them it's just by the same IP
address but a different port as it so
they like the containers themselves they
get with with the British networking
they do actually get their own IP
address it's it's really just that that
essentially yeah essentially have this
vias pair that that is you know one part
is effective you have two namespaces
right the one being in the container the
network namespace in the container and
the other one being in the host and
through the via there these two can
communicate and and the IP there is
really host local so that you know
doesn't go beyond that host so you need
to have some if you actually want to get
traffic to that internet container you
need to do some something outside of
that but I like these four local or yeah
local container docker network notes
both are nowadays unless as I said you
manually launch a container on your left
or not that interesting are widely used
right you're really looking at overlay
or whatever in a clustered set up when
you know when you're actually running
from containers in production in terms
of allocating IP addresses the bridge
mode mostly takes care of this what
about the other modes right so they are
again it very much depends on what your
setup is if you have a single host so
again to think of your laptop you
typically you know you find you can
manually do that you carve up a certain
range probably in a private IP address
range and and you're fine in a
distributed set up that is something
completely different and there it's it's
mainly about either your you know
network plugin or or third party
solution like you know calico and weave
and flannel and and whatnot they provide
something like that out of the box or
the respective container network
standard like CIOs
I have respite of support for the
plugins that do that so I pen providers
that actually manage IP addresses
throughout the cluster so they might
have a separate database for example and
assign entire IP address ranges to notes
orders and gossiping going on or
whatever did the actual way of spreading
and managing these IP address ranges at
the end of the day is but the big
challenge really is in a distributed set
up where especially if you're hitting
like you know hundreds and have more
notes you don't want to manually arrange
that and in Kalidas land it's even more
complex because you're essentially
dealing with three different and
distinct sets of IP address ranges for
the hosts for the pods and for the
services so depending on on the the
container Orchestrator you you you know
might need a more complete or advanced
solution to manage these IP addresses
ranges okay in terms of our managing
ports now we have fixed and dynamic port
allocation how do each of these work in
which cases what we use each one right
so I said with bridge mode you're
essentially you're fine because since
each each container has its own just
local but and private but has its own IP
address you don't need to you know worry
about that with host mode obviously
since the you're essentially reusing or
sharing the the network with the the
hosts you you need to take care of that
you need to manually allocate the port
see to say okay I can only have you know
one web server on port 80 for example or
or whatever it is the container one is
special because there it really depends
on what you're reusing if you're for
example in including this land it's not
a problem because they are the policies
IP per container technically by per pot
because all the containers in a pot
share share one IP address and not
well-known with nan you don't have that
problem but the biggest difference here
is really hot Coast versus bridge so
that's why I guess my bridge is still
the default
you know if we have a single darker
demon there because people don't need to
worry about Brit about allocating the
ports or or matching the ports they can
just you know each of them each of the
containers can simply use whatever port
you like I guess that's that's one of
the motivations why it's still the
default there there's quite a few things
to consider in terms of network security
with docker containers and by default
containers on the same host can
communicate with each other due to the -
- I cc switch equals true and which
means comms work by default but there
are risks that need to be considered can
you talk a little bit I'm a little bit
about these risks and here engineers can
mitigate them right I have to say that
many of these things are or some of
these things are really more of
historical interest rather than your
going forward things like links for
example between containers are or have
been deprecated so that it's not an
issue anymore it's still there so this
inter container communication ICC is
still there this flag is still there so
if you do set it to true what it
effectively means at the end of the day
is that darker the docker daemon there
will add a default rule to the for chain
in IP tables that effectively accepts
everything there and if you set it to
false and it will have a drop in there
so if you don't want that right if you
don't want that and the forward chained
and then you want to have ICC false and
with with there all the implications so
unless you know like unless you have a
really good reason to have it just you
know you know what you're doing and you
have a really good reason why you want
to have that essentially being able to
you know coming from one network
interface going to another network
interface by default or all the packages
are accepted you probably want to
scatter to false anyways and as I said
some of the issues that were there
initially around the a very primitive
way of service discovery which was
called err is called links which
essentially only worked on a single
machine so you
you ready a spell there link2cell little
ink docker containers so essentially the
idea was that you know you could
explicitly say you know link this
container to that container and then
these two containers can convert to see
each other and talk to each other via
this name and since it a it only works
on a single host or single node and B
it's it's really malleable and brittle
this link link based service discovering
linking of containers has been
deprecated anyways and and with that
quite a big chunk of the issues around
in the container communication has gone
away anyways but it's still there so you
know probably best set it to false or
III would at least do it okay so if one
container gets compromised it could
potentially access other containers on
the host and compromised them as well
what else do we need to be thinking
about in order to provide solid
configuration and mitigation around this
right so again difference between you
know one single note and and multiple
nodes where multiple nodes you typically
have to take into consideration what
kind of you know container Orchestrator
you're dealing with there in terms of
what service discovery is offered and so
on but in the simplest case for for a
single node think of the the many many
command-line options and as i said i'm
not very familiar with the the most
recent version but what the defaults
there are at the end of the day
everything what's happening there is
just essentially a fancy way to
manipulate IP tables so if you are a
network network security a security guy
you know your IP tables then at the end
of the day you can just you know look at
what with certain settings defaults or
whatever
what is the result in in in IP tables
you see all the rules there and and with
that you have a pretty good idea what is
going on what is allowed what you know
which containers can talk to what can
you do something from the host and so on
in general because you do do
you know you are dealing with with a
demon there that runs on the host you
have an attack vector there so you know
anyone who has would exist there can
essentially own all the containers there
so you really want to want to make sure
that you don't have that available from
from the outside world there are other
setups that are possible that do not use
this is a team-based approach there's
rocket they're there in the context of
cryo which is good it is specific we
have you know non non demon based
systems from a security perspective this
is certainly something that that is
worrying to up to certain darker version
it was also the problem with with
upgrading this so you you know you might
have figured there's a bug there or you
know some some security patches
necessary but he couldn't really upgrade
the docker container run time while the
containers were running you had to shut
down all the containers and so people
would you know probably wait a bit
longer than and then is advisable to
upgrade so you know there are a couple
of implications with these big fat
demons as my colleague Dan Walsh likes
to call them and yeah so nutshell that
is for for a for a single note that is
the case it gets more interesting and
more complicated in the case of multiple
hosts and like yeah container
orchestration system like communities
yeah so we're gonna dive into the
section basically in your Pokemon moldy
house containing it working just before
you do can you give your listeners a
quick explanation of what iptables is in
the simplest sense one could say it is
an Linux kernel level way of how to
route process pre-process network
packages that come in from a network
interface and made on the one hand be
forwarded to a local process so that
would be pre routing in input were from
one network interface under the network
interface that would be pre routing
forward and post routing or from one
local process to another pros
sort of the output and input so you have
different ways how you can route these
this traffic this package and
essentially what you're doing there is
you have heard that's that's the tables
element you have a long long table where
you have rules and you say if something
comes in from that network interface and
you know has this destination and so on
and so forth then drop it or you know
forwarded or whatever and this although
it's you know from the UX not very cool
or or interesting or whatever this forms
still pretty much the basis of pretty
much everything we have there there
there are nowadays you know IPS based
poker swarm has that and and in
communities we we have to starting to
see support for that as well simply
because IP tables has a certain
depending on how you use it you have a
certain you see certain limitation for
example in communities Lent
you have that you know if entry is a
couple of entries for each of the
services on every node and if you're
hitting like ten twenty thousand
services you have a very long IP to host
there and you know it just takes quite a
while until you you find something there
so if you have many many services and
you have many many entries there you you
really want something else like a PBS
but yeah now this I would say it's still
more or less the standard way so you
mean should I be eise can you explain it
I PBS is essentially a more effective
way to go about at the end of the day
you know has the same underlying kernel
structures that I'm manipulated but it's
rather than having you know a linear
search through these tables to these
these these rules there you have a I
can't really talk about the details how
it is implemented it's a more effective
way to go about that this problem of
defining how the kernel is supposed to
route the packages on the one hand
network interface and underhand local
processes and yeah I'm not like expert
the only thing I know is for sure that
apparently for for large-scale you know
services if you have many of those
then you need something like that I'm
not saying that this is the only
solution I'm just saying I've seen it it
is already part of stalkers form and in
in communities land
this was actually work led by who I why
they they push that quite a lot that IPS
is you know establishing itself as an
alternative to iptables based routing
there
right so where do we start
I know you mentioned it was somewhere on
our marketing talk in it but there must
be a little bit more to it than that
yeah yes yes so in the widest sense like
if someone hears overlay then the
question is you know what's what else is
there is there an underlay and indeed it
is so obviously before we had overlay
networks and there always will be the
underlay so the actual the actual stuff
right the wires and then Nixon and all
the stuff where it's actually happening
in the widest sense if you think about
it also the Internet is an overlay
network right
VPN many many things count as overlay
networks in the context of container and
continue orchestration we typically
think of a stricter set of overlay
networks and you know there are many
ways how you can differentiate them you
can look at what level they are
operating and so on and so forth you can
differentiate between VX land or UDP
overlay and so on and so there are many
many different ways docker Dockers worm
has its own table network built in it
has its own key value store and one
thing that one should not forget with an
overlay network you need some kind of
typically key value store distributed
key-value store which in Dawkins case is
essentially built in graft based usually
in communities land we were more or less
leveraging at CD which is also Roth base
key value store which is you know
separate process outside and yeah so you
need that to keep essentially at the
state you need to know you need to
remember who has what and you know all
the assignments and songs you need some
kind of distributed typically given your
stories I said so this overlay network
essentially defines a virtual network if
you want a software-defined network on
top of the underlying top of what is
actually there on top of what is the
actual wiring there and this means that
sits for flexible you can you know
define depending on the properties of
your olia network pretty much everything
as you need it you can
throw it away you can immediately
program it in a way that it you know
accommodates the the velocity that you
seen in container land so in a nutshell
overlay Network a virtual very highly
configurable network software affine
network on top off of an existing
physical network does make sense okay
what does dock a support for I've
aligned it works look like right so you
have a lot of of players in that space
and it hasn't really I think it has even
gone up in the last couple of years you
haven't one hand the established player
right of course you have you know the
Cisco's and and understand but
interesting their number of range of of
startups that that have done incredible
innovations there Korres for example was
flannel we've worked with with weave net
either is metal switched project calico
there there's a boy switch which is now
part of the OpenStack project um there's
a VPN there's kennel which is
essentially a kind of joint work between
calico and flannel there is from another
psyllium which is EPP every PPF based as
I have learned you don't say the EP
anymore there's a parade - there there
there are tons of these services so
essentially if you are you talking about
docker proper you essentially either use
the built-in docker overlay network or
one of the third-party as I said calico
flannel we've met and as I said psyllium
being a rather recent addition to the
whole circus but a very interesting one
because it's it's based on a PPF
yes so you talk about he's quite a bit
in your book as well don't you yeah a
little bit but you know to be honest it
the since it's such a fast-moving space
and you know projects are working and
this and that and the adding support for
everything it you know a book you can
never actually keep up to date even a
website is you know you would need to
update it pretty much every day or every
other day just to keep up to date so I
think the best that you can do in that
space is if you have already like
experience with something or preference
for something go with that or you use
the stuff that it comes out of the box
docker typically has that right has
batteries included and you know then you
have third-party integrations or plugins
that you can use I think with many
things it's a bit like a bit of like a
taste thing right or preferences things
so some people find the one solution or
the one approach cooler of course there
are differences right they are like you
know calico is always focusing on or is
always focusing still on policy stuff
whereas others you know like finals
trying to be very like UNIX see in the
sense of that's doing one thing easy
simple small not trying to do everything
and you know depends some people prefer
the one or the other all I'm saying is
that there are many there are many
things to choose from you might end up
using or evaluating two or three or four
I wouldn't be surprised if you do and
then you know stick with what you you
have the best experience with
digitalocean is the easiest cloud
platform to deploy manage and scale
applications of any size removing
infrastructure friction and providing
predictability so developers and their
teams can deploy faster and focus on
building software that customers love
with thousands of in-depth tutorials in
an active community we provide the
support you need digitalocean stands out
of the crowd due to its simplicity and
high performance with no billing
surprises try digitalocean for free by
getting a one hundred dollar
infrastructure credit at doco /sc radio
could you give a cert an example of one
of them and how you got basically
creating an overlay network with one of
those projects so like what are the
steps involved right big ones right so
you have docker with with the CM
container network model which
essentially yeah is this one company
that has established is this standard
and and follows there right and indeed
the canonical implementation there is
live network and a couple of plugins
we've has County of calico plumb grid
and so on and then on the other hand
which originally came out of Quinn it is
but nowadays is a wider accepted
standard as supported by many many
different orchestrators including you
know messes and Cloud Foundry and so on
it's the container network interface you
know and again you will see many many
different many many of the same players
did you see in CNM land like we even and
calico and the many many more plugins
from both of them others because Sienna
is is very very lightweight it's you
know I said she just you know a very
very simple interface to add or remove
capability here and so depending on
which one there you're using so if
you're using for example Dockers worm
which obviously supports CNM Dockers
Network model that looks totally
different to if you're using CNI with
you know communities even if you talk
about the same thing right if you're
looking at weave how to deploy that is
an overlay network on on dr. swarm or as
a third-party plugin under course worm
versus CNI and communities that looks
different and so it's not so useful to
say hey this is you know of course you
can say here the commands here you know
it's darker create network or network
creator can really see biggest here
anymore and then you know depending on
if you using the building or using a
third party versus CNI which is very
lightweight is that you have just to
chase a file where you have the
configuration then you say hey do that
for me and the interface really since
you're just passing over that Chase and
file to the container runtime the
container runtime then goes off does
things or that is in the other direction
to continue Wrentham says hey here I
want to have this in this done and the
rest if plug-in then does something like
you know I I PE location or overlay
network setup or whatever and then
reports that back to the
in a run time so depending on the model
in a nutshell trying to answer the
question depending on the model used CNN
Morrissey and I the actual steps look
pretty pretty different the only
advantage that you have probably is that
if you are already using a concrete
project or product like that's a calico
then moving from one you know
Orchestrator to the other might be
simpler because it's just the difference
in terms of how you set it up how you
enable it but still the underlying
characteristics in terms of you know
latency scalability reliability and so
and so forth will be the same so it's
certainly a good thing that both network
models continue network models
essentially in the nutshell of work work
pretty similar right so what's the
difference between an overlay Network
and so docker swarm nowadays this is
really the entire container Orchestrator
right and one part of that of Poker
swarm and creators and investors and
nomads many many more is how to either
out of the box or through you know third
party integrations enable the multi host
container networking right so you could
have like in docker swarm case you could
have TD the overlay network built in
where it has you know the key value
store and everything more or less
directly integrated whereas code is land
you have these are separate components
right you have the API server which is
one binary you have EDD which is one or
more other binaries running somewhere
else but still having the same
functionality so it's kind of like
monoliths versus micro service
architecture but doctors weren't really
being the entire container Orchestrator
where networking you know enabling this
networking being able that the different
containers applications running in
different containers and different nodes
can communicate with each other and also
ingress obviously is part of the
responsibility of a container
Orchestrator okay cool
here we go a bit encrypting traffic
between all containers on an overlay
Network I'm assuming this is going to be
different depending on what type of
overlay product you're using
right right right and nowadays I would
almost think or I don't have hard data
to be honest but I would say that
especially in the context of of service
measures it's increasingly popular debt
you essentially have mutual TLS between
all the endpoints involved so even
within the cluster even you know the
bunch of machines very running your
container is even there between all all
of the endpoints whatever the input
might be that you know might be that the
container itself it might be a sidecar
like again onward for example that even
between these endpoints within the
cluster everything is beautifully less
everything is encryption on the wire and
to end everything is there and then it
pretty much depends on the scale right
if you have large scale you really want
to have a service mesh that part of its
control plane actually has something
that you know takes care of the
certificates rotation and all that bits
but in general if you buy into that if
you you know are aware of the the
implications there what happens is
specially you know in a multi-tenant
environment if you're not so trusted
environment you're sharing resources
with others you probably want your like
containers all of them even within the
cluster being encrypted on the wire as
well and I'm not saying that all of the
solutions supply that out of the box but
as I said increasingly you do find like
Sto for example in this case I'm a
mother and I know there is a component
in there
I think it's called Citadel if I
remember correctly that actually takes
care of that
meticulous for every service that is
there and sometimes you as I said you
find this functionality also in what I
would consider lower level you know
things like helium or we for or flannel
or whatever that also take care of that
in in the context of you know providing
the network and on top of that they also
provide end-to-end encrypted on the wire
right so it really depends what you're
using is to who or what is responsible
for providing that safe link yes what
are some of the network plugins docker
provides and how do we use them or how
do we go about using them so would
talk about the plugins itself already a
bit right in general they are the
default ones that are there that are non
third-party whatever they're called
default or buildings or whatever that
are essentially in the one hand make
VLAN and also IP Weiland and on the
other hand they build in overlay network
so this is when you say doc a create
Network where you you can directly
create these multi host networks out of
your box and everything else actual
third-party Network plugins as I
mentioned things like calico and fennel
and and we've met and Romana element and
others that depending on what they are
based on realize things differently but
at the end of the day more or less all
address the same issue and that is
enabling applications that run in
containers on different hosts to
communicate transparently so you don't
need to you know know is the container
running on the same node or some
something else no you can just you know
from it quite a few for an application
you can just use the service discovery
that is the container Orchestrator
offers and can just talk to that other
container as if it's a local process
alright so so what are some of the
issues that often arise out of IP
address management and and here are
these addressed so in general is very
often the reason why why it's
challenging is very often dead you have
a bunch of you know notes so you might
have thirty hundred a couple of hundred
notes and you have many hundreds you
might have you know 10 20 50 whatever
container is per per notes we end up
having hundreds or a thousands of
containers and that means that
especially and now I'm talking a little
bit with the assumption that we're
talking Kalidas land is not the case for
every container Orchestrator where you
essentially have this requirement you
have an IP per per container and that is
something that you know it means that
you you need to be able to carve out
many many IP addresses and that
how do you go about that how do you
reuse stuff how do you assign stuff to
you
centrally manages to use somehow gossip
it through the entire cluster so the
challenges there are really the
combination of scale and and speed as
you need to be able to manage large
number in in yeah in a rather quick way
the other challenge which is problem of
challenge it's more to do with the fact
that cloud providers still haven't
widely adopted ipv6 because in ipv6 case
you have many many more add resist here
you don't get after the big challenge
there or not as much for an awful
challenge but we are seeing only you
know slowly support for for ipv6 in
container land so it's not not the case
that every container solution has
already you know ipv6 support out of the
box when we get there I guess then this
this challenges away a little easier to
address them can you give us an example
of how you normally go by UPS
I guess managing these IP addresses is
it basically just up to the orchestrator
you just I'll leave everything up to the
orchestrator I mean how much a manual
intervention is actually involved so for
example if you have communities you
essentially you're required to that
depends but also the Installer and and
good practices around that and you know
environment are you you know installing
it something yourself with you know cube
EDM for example or or are you launching
a committees engine nice it's called now
cluster where you don't get to do these
things directly but at the end of the
day you need to carve out certain IP
address ranges so they're good practices
they're way say you know here's what you
should do and here's what you should not
do sometimes it's it's a matter of
policy sometimes you know organization
says okay we only assign private ranches
it pretty much depends on the
environment are you on premises are in
the cloud what what your preference is
there are but essentially at the end of
the day you would add install time more
or less define these
IP address ranges in the case of coitus
as I said you need one for one range for
nodes which typically is you know you
don't change the number of notes every
day and until you you reach a hundred
thousand you typically have a rather
good idea what what's the the number of
nodes in your cluster is although that
might you know throw out the skimming
that might change a little bit but it's
not that you know you have today ten and
tomorrow fifty and the next day five
hundred or whatever note so that is
fairly doable with parts it's it's
really tough because there can be many
pots and they come and go and every time
you create a new part you you need a new
IP address to knit her son in Europe he
address and services on the one hand
they're much more stable right so that's
what that's the defining feature of a
service in community distillate it
provides a stable of virtual IPs and a
peer is not connected to a network
interface so you can ping it but because
of the implementations it's currently
done through the proxy it effectively
means that in on the routing layer to
actually get a package to to a part that
sits behind the service it needs to
update potentially a lot of different
rules across all the notes on through IP
tables and that is certainly a limiting
factor there which is orthogonal to the
IP location but still you need to take
that into into consideration when using
IP tables directly yeah so in a nutshell
pretty much depends on environment your
preferences or policies organizationally
and the container Orchestrator you're
using they have different requirements
for what kind of ranges you need to
either before you're at install time or
if you have you know typically in in
credits length you you would use a CNI
plugin that takes care of that
dynamically which is probably one of the
best ways to go about if you can if you
can afford that right so Infoblox I know
it's not open driver for CNI but you
know if you have a full-blown IBM IP
address management solution
you might end up paying someone some
serious money right I'm not I don't know
the details about the prices but I can
imagine that you know it's you know this
this quality comes with with premiere a
hefty price label there yeah yeah so
we're just going to move into a short
section on orchestration hmm so there's
a few different roles involved in
orchestration such as organizational
parameters scheduling automated health
checks auto scaling upgrade strategies
and service discovery can you talk a
little bit about these right so if you
think about it what the role of a
container orchestrate and essentially
it's about the lifecycle management of
containers right so you as a user say
hey you know here is my container image
run it for me somewhere and the
container Orchestrator you you know you
have an overview of old notes about how
they are utilized you might have certain
preferences you for example look as user
could say hey make sure that this part
or this container in this case part is
included this specific lands on a note
that it has I don't know that is SSD
back door has a GPU or whatever well you
could say you know make sure that these
containers don't gets killed in the same
node you might have you know some
multi-tenancy requirements or don't
schedule database containers on the same
notes as I don't know some some
stateless notification whatever the
policy there is and you also have
organizational primitives which like
traditionally for example marathon you
had things like groups where you can
group your applications together and
then say essentially you know hard code
dependencies can say you know let's say
the front and should only be started
when the backend is available and
beckoned passes all health checks one of
the innovations that could this really
brought to the table and and that is was
pretty well described by but the
Googlers from their lessons learned from
you know running running pork in product
refer for more than decayed and then try
new things with Omega our labels and
labels have
varies very lightweight and very very
flexible way of organizing things so
rather than having a hierarchical is a
grouping essentially means hierarchical
fixed way of viewing how things are
organized you're labeling things and
that allows different stakeholders to
manage to group things in different ways
and what is important to them so for
example for someone a release engineer
whatever let's say you know I'm only
interested in knowing is that container
in development testing staging or
production right that's all I care about
I don't care who it belongs to
whatever I only care about that someone
else might say you know building or
whatever internal customers might say
you know to me it's important to us that
you know is that someone who has a big
part or a like you know internal budget
holder number or whatever someone else
might say you know I'm interested in how
what kind of security checks or policies
have been applied so each and every one
gets to use their labels and can query
using these labels and with that
dynamically organize the view on the
containers themselves as with
preferences they have to do their job
best so these are the organizational
primitives and then there are a number
of things that you know affect or make
it easier for the orchestrator to
automate things like you know health
checking being able to automatically
scale that's typically by default based
on low level metrics like CPU
utilization memorization and
increasingly we're moving over to custom
metrics where you go things like in my
application I typically have you know
50,000 requests per seconds and you know
now I see an increase to 80,000 and that
means I want to have three more replicas
for example and then upgrade strategies
so in what way are you rolling out a new
version I replace an existing we are
doing a rolling upgrade and so on and so
forth and service discovery which yeah
so labels our kubernetes only concept of
a yes labels to organize
any kind of object and included is it's
not you know it's anything you can you
know label apart you can label
deployment you can label and no you can
label and depending on the kind of
object they serve different roles right
and administrator might have a different
use case for a label too you know
somehow make sure that they know what
what notes there are like you know label
you know with different hardware
characteristics or label with in what
rack they are or whatever but never they
need to do their job versus I don't know
someone and the security team looking at
things like different namespaces or
whatever and labeling things there so
that they know what what's going on and
they are also first-class citizens in
the sense of that you can query them so
you could say you know give me all
containers or pots will in inquiries
that are owned by Kim and that are in
stage production and that have not been
updated for three weeks right so we have
these labels and by by the selectors by
using thing a bit like sequel in a very
very very simple way of doing like a
very stupid naive way of doing sequel
you can combine these different labels
and and through the selectors get
exactly the subsets of you know whatever
kind of resource or object parts
services notes or whatever it is that
that you are interested in so what are
some of the other organizational
primitives so that's as I said that's
originally what you would find
traditionally in marathon other places
would be things like groups where you
would have a hierarchical start
aesthetic ordering organization how you
actually declare dependencies and and
group things and so on
and one innovation that could this
brought to the table was labels and in
these labels and and I'm not sure if
others I'm not sure for example if
nomads swarm or marathon have picked it
up labels but yeah that's that's the I
would argue the most flexible way to
organize things and that's the nowadays
I would argue that the dominant with
qualities being the dominant container
orchestrated at the dominant way of
organizational primitives there but so
in terms of orchestrators we've got the
likes of docker swarm mode fetching me
sauce heshie Corp sno-med and incur
bonitas I guess so so which platforms to
these run on do they do they run on all
platforms or yep okay so you can think
of of these container orchestrators a
bit like a different functionality but a
bit like like a pass right what do you
need to run a pass well you need an
operating system right typically you
need some Linux distribution or whatever
and then you can install that pass could
be in a single node could be distributed
whatever but pretty much the same thing
is happening there and originally as I
said it was called container
orchestrators typically nowadays the
marketing term is caas so container as a
service right like pass platform as a
service this is CAS casts sometimes so
you know if if you want to be cool you
go like hey which casts you you got the
iock when it is the curse were messes
nobody now it
was quite interesting for some let's say
three years from roughly 2014 to 2017
and remember I before I joined redhead
in beginning of 2017 I used to work at
mesosphere on messes marathon DCOs so
around the time from 2015 to 2017 and
that was pretty much day there you know
the high high point of the container
orchestration Wars so that that was
where no one really knew because
cleanest was was very new just came out
docker swarm was you know docker
everything was stalker so it sounded
like and indeed if the idea was that
maybe talker wouldn't make it and messes
marathon had also quite a big mind chair
so it was at some point in time you
could say you know yeah you would have
two or three equally powerful and and
widely used systems then later on heshie
corp entered to the container
orchestration with with nomad which has
a slightly different focus and and and
orientation but it's actually we you
know besides those we obviously have
many many more things that also started
to do containers all there the
configuration management systems somehow
started to the container orchestration
as well and at the end of the day by
2017 end of 2017 cone it is essentially
one this container orchestration war so
you can nowadays it doesn't matter who
you ask
it's it's a bit like you know yes there
are people that use freebsd and that BST
or whatever but linux is dominating
pretty much everything ninety percent or
whatever is linux out there in the same
way like it or not
committees has has you know with
beginning of 2018 has essentially it's
it's supported everywhere everyone has
to you know even big big amazon at some
point in time
AWS hit who also support communities in
their offerings so it's fair to say that
nowadays communities is the dominating
container orchestrated that doesn't mean
that that the other is are gone it you
know people still are using swarm of
stable still using missiles marathon and
nomads it's just that nowadays there is
no question if you want to get into that
game the question is just you know
should I directly jump to functions the
service server that is land
why should I still be dealing with with
containers but the question is not you
know should I should I you know be doing
messes former nomads or communities if
you know if you want to when I have a
good good guarantee that your knowledge
is directly applicable than maybe
Kalitta since the best choice now yeah
so you mentioned anodes a few times are
they a kubernetes concept I'm assuming
they're a host for a container or a
collection of containers yes it's just
as just a host like the the the
technical the Kalitta documentation uses
note or work a note as that's the one
host or the one virtual machine or
physical machine that actually hosts the
container runtime and and the the other
bits that are there cube proxy the
cubelet and so on that runs the
containers for you here so what are the
main components and communities in what
are that you responsible for
right so in in a very high-level there
are two parts and included is the one
thing is you know called the control
plane previously co2 master I find
controlling much much better because
it's you know actually is you know it's
not just one binary it's it's a couple
of things it's the API server the
controller manager the implements all
the control loops if you for example in
dealing with deployments and services
and whatnot for each of these resources
you have a respective controller which
technically is just a goroutine in the
controller manager and then you have to
cut the scheduler that actually you know
does this mapping off here you have a
container actually a pod in coitus and
here is a node where where I'm running
this this pod on so the decision on
which node to launch a pop and then you
have to work on notes
typically you know nowadays you might
have 20 30 40 nodes usually and on each
of the worker nodes you have at least
three things running the cubelet which
you can think of the kind of like the
local supervisors alright in the same
way that you have
API server that use EDD to keep it
stayed around in a control plane you
have as a local note level supervisor
you have to cubelet that then talks to
the container runtime which is for
example docker OCI based things like run
ze or whatever rocket so the container
runtime that actually you know knows how
to pull a container image from registry
how to launch that container and so on
and so forth the Manchus lifecycle of a
single container and then you have cue
proxy which is part of the Cunha DS
service discovery story and realizes and
establishes these virtual IPS for the
services so essentially make sure that
there is traffic that comes from within
the cluster from some other pot and and
finds its way to a certain part that
that sits behind the service so these
are the components that that run on each
of the worker nodes and obviously you
need a container registry for the
runtime to holder the container image
and then at least in case of cádiz you
need
typically what what an atom takes care
of some kind of external user management
so communities doesn't you know you
can't create users or whatever they're
there there are identities for for
applications called software service
accounts which represent identities for
applications but CODIS doesn't like it
can use you can understand you know this
is too user and this is the group or
whatever but it doesn't manage users for
you so you need some some LDAP Active
Directory SEM or Kerberos whatever
something external that manages your
users and group and then you can you
know if integrations to bring that in to
committees can you give us a bit of an
overview of kubernetes networking like
so containers can communicate with all
other containers without net our nodes
can communicate with all containers and
vice versa without net and the IP
container sees itself is the same IP is
others see it is it right Reverend so
what's interesting there is I think the
fact that
Unity's is not prescriptive there right
courtesy eccentric just says look here
are a couple of requirements I have and
you know how you realize them I don't
care as long as these three requirements
that you mentioned are met right so
there is no netting there is her
technically it's per pot so pot is a a
collection of a couple of containers
that are guaranteed to be scheduled on
the same note that each of them can
communicate with any other in that
container without any netting right so
each of them has each part has its own
IP gets in you assigned if it restarts
some even in the same node has always a
an IP and the nodes can talk to the
containers in the containers can talk to
notes and amongst each others without
netting and also which is also different
to darker where depending on what you
are using you have different eyepiece
that you see from the outside world and
inside world that yeah the IP the
container sees itself is it's the same
that that address other hosts or
containers are pots in the network see
see that container and that is
essentially because it's not
prescriptive it just says here
requirement please a lot of flexibility
to tohow implement right you can do that
bare metal with with some manual
configuration you can use any kind of as
the end there
the parent site is however that because
Kandy's doesn't supply anything out of
the box there that you effectively are
forced to roll your own coolies
distribution right this is one of the
decisions that you if you want to use
create this you need to make right you
cannot there is not anything out of the
box like you have with in doctor's case
with the darker overlay network they can
just use right so at the end of the day
your decision is either I roll my own
career situation and there are other
bits and pieces where you also need to
make decisions where you say okay
especially on premises you know what
kind of storage am I gonna use or
ingress how do I get traffic in there so
there a couple of other things but most
importantly this coding is networking
there is nothing out of the box there so
if you don't do it yourself then you can
use one of the over thirty certified
communities distributions but at the end
of the day you need to use aqueous
distribution right in the same way that
you cannot use two dynix kernel on its
own you need to have a Linux
distribution in the same way here you
have you're dealing with a Korea's
distribution and if you'll roll it on
your own or you know pay us or someone
else to do it that's something that's a
different discussion right that spy
versus build but you have to deal with
it coolness distribution and one of the
main reasons is exactly the communities
networking okay what are some of the
distributions are there's so many SS
there over 35 or whatever one of them I
can talk about that's that's what pays
my bills is openshift has been around
for quite a while but there's there's so
many like to be clear that the most
interesting one I would argue is if you
are using one of the managed community
services of the big three right so if
you're in Google or Asher or AWS then
each of them obviously has their own
Korea's distribution they typically are
not very public about that right it's
just there you don't really get to see
the the bits and I mean of course you
see sometimes you have options you could
say okay I'm I want to use final versus
calico or whatever and there are certain
preferences as well so of the cloud
provider towards certain solutions but
you don't really get to see
how did the whole distribution looks
like right and then there are you know
very minimal ones that you know had to
be very opinionated but a very
lightweight there are things like
overshift that you know the one hand
it's a kundus distribution but on the
other hand also provides a lot of pest
functionality ships with a container
registry and the build system and so on
and so forth so that it's like is that
they're currently already over 30
certified so the CN CF the cloud native
compute foundation essentially it has a
very lightweight process and she says
okay here the conformance test run them
yeah so each and every one can just
simply you know figure out for
themselves if they if they are compliant
or not and once you're done you sent it
in and and then and then since it's so
transparent there is no you know
politics or whatever involved if you
posit York informant and you can call
yourself a yeah and certified Kunis
distribution so say I'm a developer and
I want to sit up some orchestration on
kubernetes locally so that I can test it
can I just sit up kubernetes
distribution locally in order to develop
and test is that easy enough to do yeah
so typically for developer workflows you
would have things like mini cube or
Cunha dis as part of a photographer
desktop there are there's many shifts
which is open shift out of the box in
the VM so essentially what you have is
more or less in all cases you have a VM
that essentially wraps up all the
dependencies has essentially a single
node set up and all you need to do is
depending on on the kind of offering
sometimes it's still I only sometimes
it's a nice clickety-click UI but you
essentially just launch a via a VM that
has all the components in there and
they're actually pretty great they're
like for most things they are they are
perfectly okay obviously what you can't
really do is having the effect of a real
distributed system I'm not even talking
about scale testing or whatever they're
I'm I'm really talking about you know
what happens if you have networked
petitions and and delays between
different nodes and so you simply cannot
do that with we were just obvious right
if you have everything in one VM you
simply cannot know how how your
application really works in distributed
setup but for you know oh I want to try
that out and what I could
by something whatever they are perfectly
fine and and very straightforward to set
up there is not much that you need there
I mean you need some some VM driver
there get it from vertol box or whatever
but very straightforward to set up okay
so I've got another section on a service
discovery we're getting pretty close to
time just see if I can spring a couple
of questions in terms of registering a
container what happens when the
scheduler dies in registered containers
keep running I'm essentially the
containers are now running rogue is that
correct yes yes so essentially it's
pretty pretty much the case with all the
different container orchestrators dead
if the scheduler or whatever it is might
be the API server in Queens case or
whatever a control plane component dies
then all the containers on the worker
nodes continue to work they don't notice
that the only thing that you cannot do
is you cannot do updates you cannot you
know for example roll out a new version
or if one of the pots or containers dies
and and you know it's you know it will
not be scheduled somewhere else because
there is no control thing around to
figure out that this container has died
it needs to be you know launched
somewhere else so as long as you don't
have any like network service discovery
related like depending on some fqdn or
whatever that it's not there anymore or
that doesn't resolve ton of IP you
should be fine right so everything and
typically you know I mean you do
typically it's a scheduler or if you I
said whatever dies you typically trying
to get it back up and running in a
certain point of time as I said you know
you know letting it but letting it in
that state for four weeks and weeks but
you know you're trying to fix that and
if it comes up within within an hour or
two that's fine right and and typically
also dealing with a couple of replicas
there so if you don't if you'd only have
one replica of a pot or of a container
there then maybe even trouble but if you
have a couple of them and and due to
whatever reason one of them or two of
them dies okay maybe you know your
application slows down a bit but it's
still there and it's still serving so
when the scheduler comes up again does
its find the rogue containers I mean how
does a gobby have fun
so this very much depends on the
container orchestration system but at
the end of the day what happens is you
have on each of the nodes you have
in local supervisors and kids of Korean
distance that would be the culet and
that essentially sends you know
heartbeats to the control plane
component saying yeah I'm still around
I'm still good time so good them yeah
maybe in cases usually also saying like
hey you know I have son so many
containers running and you know I have
this memory pressure or whatever other
status information it sends to the
control and so that that will just
continue and as long as things are
happening on all of the different sides
so you know both in control plane and
and on the node or nodes did you know
just three starts and self heels and and
at some point in time picks up you know
where it has left off if the the state
if the distributed states or like the
cluster state it's not corrupted that is
probably the hardest bit right if you
for example in case of conducive if EDD
is down like you know you can still it's
the same it doesn't really matter if ed
city is bounded then you can change the
state right it doesn't really matter if
the API server is up because it can't
change anything you cannot read you
cannot write the state it doesn't matter
so did the assumption really is that's
why you typically run you know three or
five at city service they're together
that that you have a guarantee premature
guarantee that the dead city never goes
down and what's LCD for for Canadians
it's zookeeper for messes and songs for
so each of the container orchestrators
has they are typically distributed
key-value system that has you know this
is t the ultimate system of records that
knows exactly the state of the entire
cluster
yeah so does that component go down
occasionally as well and if it does I
guess I guess basically you've just got
a shuttle you containers down right so
I've also noticed you've got the
kubernetes cookbook right and you've got
the kubernetes security you're working
on are they done or are you still
working on those yeah so the kritis came
out in March I believe so that is out
there it's as far as I gather quite
successful so a lot of people I get you
know people tell me it's coal and and I
see it online and whatnot committee
security which I'm writing with less
rice from from micro security we
literally just submitted the the final
draft so we're now going in product
and I think it should be out by the end
of 2018 so like you know October and
November who knows around that time so
we're looking forward to those
especially the security god so yeah
thanks for joining us today yeah Michael
it's been an educational and fun cool
thanks a lot for having me Kim that's
really fun
for software engineering radio this was
Kim cardio hoist thanks digitalocean is
the easiest cloud platform to deploy
manage and scale applications of any
size we're moving infrastructure
friction and providing predictability so
developers and their teams can deploy
faster and focus on building software
that customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials in an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
100 dollar infrastructure credit at doco
/sc radio thanks for listening to se
radio an educational program brought to
you by Archer police software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at SE -
radio net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of SU radio is licensed under
creative commons license' two-point-five
thanks for listening